Narrator: Part 2
Emma Barnett: YouŐre listening to the story of Anthony Ray Hinton.
He spent three decades in prison for a crime he didnŐt commit,
but he didnŐt give up,
and eventually his case was taken up by the Equal Justice Initiative,
a group in Alabama that fights racism in the US justice system.
Anthony Ray Hinton: What gave me hope, more than anything,
was when I met Bryan Stevenson from the Equal Justice Initiative,
and I saw that his skin was the same colour as my skin,
and I felt for the first time that he being an African-American,
he would do everything in his earthly power to try and prove my innocence.
And I was right about that. He, along with the lawyers and the EJI staff,
they worked for sixteen long years to win my freedom.
Sixteen long years that they had to fight back and forth in the courts,
arguing that this was wrong, and finally we won our Đ
my Đ freedom, April the 3rd, 2015.
Emma Barnett: What was that moment like?
Anthony Ray Hinton: Well, I never will forgetÉ
I got up and I called Byan Stevenson and he told me,
he said, ÔRay, you going home.Ő And I hadnŐt heard that word, ÔhomeŐ, in 30 years.
And I sat on the floor and I cried like a baby.
And all the young men that was around me saw that I was crying,
and they, probably, at the moment,
they probably thought that I had got some bad news.
And IŐll never forget, one of the young guys, he came up,
he said, ÔPop, something wrong?Ő And I looked up at him
and I said, er, ÔIŐm going home.Ő
And they told me how proud they was that I was going home,
and even some gave me advice, and:
ÔPop, itŐs a different world out there than what you was used to.Ő
Me being locked up 30 years, and the world had passed me by,
and I got my very first taste of modern technology when I got in my best friendŐs car Đ Lester.
He asked me, when they released me, ÔWhere do you wanna go first?Ő
and I said, ÔI want you to take me where they laid my motherŐs body.Ő
Emma Barnett: Because your mother died while you were in prison?
Anthony Ray Hinton: Yes. And he said, ÔOK.Ő
And I see him fidgeting with Đ what I thought he was trying to find
Đ a radio station so I could hear some good music.
And as we got on the road, I hear this white lady voice.
She said, ÔIn one tenth of a mile, turn right.Ő And it frightened me!
I said, ÔWhat the hell?Ő And I looks over at him,
heŐs laughing and heŐs looking at how hysterical
I must have been looking and I was too afraid to look back.
He veer off to the right and he said, ÔThatŐs no white lady back there,Ő he said.
ÔThis is GPS, I told you everything have changed,Ő he said.
ÔShe gonna tell me exactly how to get to the cemetery.Ő He said, ÔThis is modern technology.Ő
I said, ÔYou telling me that we donŐt have to stop at the filling station
and ask for directions no more?Ő
He said, ÔYes, I told you that you gonna have to learn everything over again.Ő
Emma Barnett: Do you feel pleasure? Are you able to enjoy your life?
Do you believe in your freedom?
Anthony Ray Hinton: I believe in my freedom, I enjoy life every day.
I enjoy life more than anything.
I realize that I took my life and my freedom for granted,
and it wasnŐt until I got locked up, and I realized that
there is nothing in this world more important than your freedomÉ
and I promised myself that I would enjoy my freedom until the day I die,
after spending 30 years of pure hell in a cage.
I donŐt care when it raining, I walks in the rain because
for 30 years rain was not allowed to fall on my body,
and every time it rain I walks in the rain, it feel, like, so cool and so refreshing.
Freedom is the most beautiful thing any man or woman can have.